Guide to the Frank Baker Collection of Wesleyana and British Methodism, 1536-1996 and undated RL.00413
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Visual Materials Series, 1567-1990 and undated, 35 boxes, approximately 8500 items
  - Maps Subseries, circa 1670-1990 and undated, 4 boxes
    - British counties: (Box VM 27)
      - Cheshire, A New and Accurate Map of the County Palatine of Cheshire; A New and Accurate Map of the County of Suffolk...Divided into Hundreds, London: C. Smith, 2nd ed., corrected, 1808, 2 maps, color, 25 x 20 (Box VM 28)
      - Cornwall, A New and Accurate Map of the County of Cornwall, from an Actual Survey, Made by Thomas Martyn, seven sheets and title, 1" to 1 mile, Thosas Martyn, 1748, 8 sheets (Box VM 28)
        Title sheet shows "The Arms of the Nobility and Gentry that have Subscrib'd for the Map." FB has added a diagram page that shows the seven sectional maps, on following sheets, in relation to the whole of Cornwall. Title page approx. 53" x 11"; maps approx. 28.5" x 21.5," w/one smaller.
      - Derbyshire, published by Henry Teesdale, 1830, 1 sheet, color, 13.5 x 18.5 (Box VM 27)
      - Norfolk, A New and Accurate Map of the County of Norfolk, London: Robert Sayer Map and Printseller, before 1745, 1 sheet, 41.5 x 26 (Oversize-folder 2)
        Colored map containing list of M.P.'s, including Sir Robert Walpole; prospect of Norwich; plan of Great Yarmouth; and index of towns and villages.
      - Northumberland, published by Henry Teesdale, 1830, 1 sheet, color, 13.5 x 18.5 (Box VM 27)
      - Oxfordshire, The County of Oxford, Surveyed Anno MDCCLXVI & VII, and Engraved by Thomas Jefferys, Geographer to His Majesty, 1" to 1 m., 1768-1769, 4 sheets, complete, 30.5 x 24 (Box VM 31)
        Large bound volume. Includes plan of University of Oxford.
      - A Map of Surrey...of Middlesex...of Kent...of Hartfordshire...of Essex, 1811, 5 sheets, 16 x 20 (Box VM 27)
      - Map of Warminster District, [undated?], 1 sheet, 16 x 14 (Box VM 27)
      - Warwickshire, A New Map of the County of Warwick, Divided into Hundreds, 1804 Jan. 26, 1 sheet, color, 20.5 x 19 (Box VM 27)
      - The East Riding of Yorkshire, undated, 3 items: 2 plain, one with handwritten notes: 1786 Plan for Hull Circuit (Box VM 28)
      - County Ordinance Surveys, 1867, 1883, 1888, and 1900, 4 items (Box VM 28)
    - British towns and estates: (Box VM 27)
      - Cities and towns--engravings, notes, and printed materials, 1804-1806, 1950, 1990, and undated, 15 items (Box VM 23)
        Six engraved printed maps (color and black-and-white) of Derby, Durham, Exeter, Hereford, Winchester, Worchester, to "accompany The Beauties of England and Wales." Also, miscellaneous 20th century printed maps and other materials.
      - Two ordnance maps of Cave Castle Estate, Yorkshire, 1852-1855, 2 items, unfolding to 39 x 25.5 (Box VM 23)
        Maps of South Cave, No. 224 and Cave Sands and Broomfleet, No. 238A, both surveyed in 1852 and engraved in 1855; heavily hand-annotated through 1899 or later.
      - Bartholomew's Plan of Cambridge, undated, 1 sheet, 14.5 x 21 (Box VM 27)
      - Location Map of the Centre of Harrogate, [undated?] (Box VM 27)
      - Plan of the City and Environs of Bradford, [undated?] (Box VM 27)
      - Tithe Redemption Commission, Q22588, as of June 30 1843, photographic extract (Box VM 28)
        Bird's eye view of unknown area bounded by Oole and Itterby Roads, black and white.
      - London and other cities, ordnance surveys, 1894-1923, 45 maps, 41 x 29 (Box VM 30)
        Circa 45 maps, most of London, but also Edinburgh, Hull, Liverpool, Manchester, and other cities.
      - Norwich, A Plan of the City of Norwich, 1741, 1 sheet, 32 x 26 (Box VM 32)
      - Plan of an Estate in the Parish of Raithby in the County of Lincoln, offered for sale in lots on the 1848..., 1848?, 30 x 19 (Oversize-folder 1)
    - London: (Box VM 27)
      - London, 1765-1777, 1799, and undated, 9 items (Box VM 23)
        Four engraved printed maps of London, 1765-1777; one map drawn by FB of "Wesley's Spitalfields, from R. Horwood's Plan, 1799"; and miscellaneous notes and 20th century printed material.
      - An Improvised Plan of the Cities of London and Westminster and Borough of Southwark, including the New Buildings, Roads, to the Present Year 1765 (Box VM 27)
      - Shoreditch, Norton Fullgate and Coppergate Without (photocopy) (Box VM 27)
      - Aldersgate Ward with its divisions into precincts and parishes (photocopy) (Box VM 27)
      - Etching of London landscape (Box VM 27)
      - Map of London, Westminster, and Southwark in Wesley's Day, showing the locality of some of the principal places mentioned in the Journal (Box VM 27)
      - An Accurate Plan of the Cities of London and ... [cut off], 1765 (Box VM 27)
      - An Accurate Map of the Countries Twenty Miles round London drawn from actual Surveys, describing the cities, borough, k market towns, churches, seats, roads (Box VM 27)
      - An Accurate Map of the Country Sixteen Miles round London drawn and engraved from an actual survey (Box VM 27)
      - London, extending from the Head of the Paddington Canal West to the West India Docks, East, 1806 (Box VM 27)
      - The City Guide or a Pocket Plan of London, Westminster, and Southwark, with the New Buildings to this Present Year 1763 (Box VM 27)
      - London in 1741-45, by John Rocque, 1740s? (20th century reprint), 2 copies, 31.5 x 21.5 inches (Oversize-folder 1)
      - A New and Accurate Plan of the Cities of London and Westminster and Borough of Southwark with the New Roads and Buildings to the present Year 1799 from a late Survey to which is added many useful tables, views &c., circa 1799 (20th century reprint), 1 sheet, 43 x 36 (Oversize-folder 1)
    - Roads: (Box VM 27)
      - Roads, 1765-1782 and undated, 20 engravings (Box VM 23)
        Engraved maps depicting roads throughout mid-18th century England, though especially routes from London to other cities. Most of these prints originally appeared in various issues of The Gentleman's Magazine. Includes FB's numbered key plus his notes about other maps that appeared in the magazine from the 1740s-1780s. Also included here, one b/w engraving, "The Turnpike," undated.
      - A Map of the Roads of England and Wales, undated, published by P. Wogan, Dublin, 1 sheet, 18 x 21 (Box VM 27)
      - An Accurate Map of the Road from London to the Land's End in Cornwall, Passing through Salisbury, Exeter, Plymouth, etc. and The Road from Exeter to Truro, [undated?], 1 sheet, 8.5 x 18 (Box VM 27)
    - Other maps:
      - Canals, 1753-1779 and undated, 24 engravings (Box VM 23)
        Engraved prints depicting the routes of existing and planned canals throughout mid-18th century England. Most of these prints originally appeared in various issues of The Gentleman's Magazine. Includes FB's notes, which list cities, routes, known or conjectured dates of individual maps, and a numbered key.
      - A Map of all the Earth and how after the Flood it was Divided among the Sons of Noah, by J. Moxon, Hydrographer to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty, circa late 17th/early 18th century, B/W engraving, 18 x 15.5 (Box VM 27)
        Map of the world, with biblical images around all borders; at extreme eastern edge, reproduces 16th/17th century cartographic error of California depicted as an island. Dedication reads "To the most Reverend Father in God Gilbert Lord Arch Bishop of Canterbury His Grace Primate of all England and Metropolitan This Map is humbly Dedicated, by Joseph Moxon."
        [Attention: CLOSED to patron access until conservation is completed. Please consult with Research Services staff before coming to use this material.]
      - Canaan, or The Land of Promise, Possessed by the Children of Israel and Travelled through by our Saviour Jesus Christ; and His Apostles. Translated by Joseph Moxon, Hydrographer to the Kings most Excellent Majesty, at Amsterdam by Nicolaus Visscher with Priviledge of y H. M. Lords y States Generall, circa late 17th/early 18th century, B/W engraving, 18 x 15 (Box VM 27)
        Dedication reads: "To the Right Reverend Father in God Humphrey Lord Bishop of London this Mapp is humbly Dedicated by J. Moxon." Verso autograph inscription: "Elizabeth Stockes her hand and Pen December the 28 1790 Amen." Other notes on the verso show the calculation of various people's ages based on birth and death dates from 1695-1802.
      - World maps, 1757-1947 and undated, 11 items (Box VM 27)
        Color and black-and-white engraved maps, and one colored modern printed map, of various places around the world, generally from areas associated with the spread of Methodism in the 18th century. Extracted from Universal Magazine and other publications; sizes range from approximately 10x8 to 18x14. Includes the following maps (short titles): India beyond the Ganges, with the Oriental Islands 1762; Island of Guadaloupe and LaMarie Galante, 1759; Celestial Globe rectified for the Age and Birth-Place of Hesiod, undated; Improved Map of Asia, 1762; Island of Martinico with its Towns, Forts,and Batteries, 1759; Island of Minorca, 1781; Maryland with the Delaware Counties and the Southern Part of New Jersey, 1757; New and Correct Map of the West Indies, 1762; and New and Accurate Map of Quebec and its Boundaries, 1787. Last and most modern item is a map of Christianity around the world, 1947 Dec. 20.
      - Methodism in Lincolnshire, after 1936, ordnance map, 45.5 x 36 (Oversize-folder 1)
        British ordnance map of Lincolnshire, adapted and retitled to indicate birthplaces and historical significance of, among others, JW, Richard Watson, and Robert Carr Brackenbury. A two-page typed narrative/explication has also been pasted in. On a separate sheet, approx. 12x36", is a detailed visual timeline, ca. 1900 of Methodism in Lincolnshire from its beginnings to about 1900, including the Grimsby, Hull and Lincoln Districts, with numers of members by circuit graphed in conjunction with the current minister.
      - The River Avon from the Severn to the Citty of Bristol, surveyed by Capt. Grenville Collins and dedicated to "The Right Worshipfull Robert Yates, Esqr., Mayor of Bristoll, and Master of the Merchants Hall in that Citty," [1693], B/W engraving, 33 x 20 (Box VM 32)
        Damage to item prevented close examination, but tentatively dated to 1693 based on two WorldCat records.
      - Miscellaneous modern black-and-white photocopies of Kingston-on-Humber and other districts in England, showing churches and other sites, after 1960 (Oversize-folder 3)
  - Places Subseries, 1756-1973 and undated, 2 boxes
    Engraved prints of landscapes and architectural sites, mainly in England. Items in this subseries are pictorial only, not cartographic--maps are arranged in a separate subseries, above. These prints were collected from a variety of books, serials, and other unidentified publications, with one of the most frequent sources being The Modern Universal British Traveller, which appeared in several editions in the late 18th century. Although they vary greatly in type, date, and size, they are predominantly prints from copper-plate engravings from the 1760s-1780s, with the most common size being about 14" x 9". There are also smaller format prints, mainly from steel-plate engravings, that date from as late as the 1840s. Arranged in alphabetical order, primarily by English county or city name; there are also places beyond England and topical headings for various types of buildings. Unsorted engravings are filed at the end, followed by folders of images in other formats, such as clippings and photographic plates from later books and serials.
    - Abbeys, churches, priories, circa 1780, 1829-1840s, 16 engravings (Box VM 23)
    - Baltimore, undated, colored engraving (Box VM 23)
    - Bristol, circa 1780, 1840s, 7 engravings (Box VM 23)
    - Cambridge, circa 1780, 6 engravings (Box VM 23)
    - Castles and homes, circa 1780, 1840s, and undated, 2 folders, 29 engravings in b/w and color (Box VM 23)
    - Cheshire and Chester, circa 1780, 1840s, 8 engravings (Box VM 23)
    - Cornwall, circa 1780, 1845, 12 engravings (Box VM 23)
    - Devonshire and Derbyshire, circa 1780, 1840s, 11 engravings (Box VM 24)
    - Durham, circa 1780, 10 engravings (Box VM 24)
    - Gloucestershire, circa 1780, 1840, 4 engravings (Box VM 24)
    - Hull and Lincolnshire districts, hand-drawn graph documenting ministers' appointments and rise and fall of membership, circa 1900 (Oversize-folder 3)
      Hand-colored, hand-drawn linear graph, 27 x 11 inches, which links data on the ministers of various Methodist circuits in Hull and Lincolnshire and the rise and fall of membership. Includes small portraits of some ministers. The last data on the graph is for the year 1900. Fragile.
    - Ireland, circa 1780-1845 and undated, 9 engravings (Box VM 24)
    - Kent, circa 1814, engraving (Box VM 24)
    - Lancashire and Lancaster, circa 1780-1844 and undated, 17 engravings (Box VM 24)
    - Leicestershire, circa 1780, 1844, 4 engravings (Box VM 24)
    - Lincolnshire, circa 1780, 1844, 7 engravings (Box VM 24)
    - Liverpool, 1845-1846 and undated, 7 engravings (Box VM 24)
    - London, circa 1757, 1805, and undated, 14 engravings (Box VM 24)
    - London, west front of the Wesleyan Centenary Hall and Mission House, 1839 (Box VM 7)
    - Manchester, 1844-1845 and undated, 6 engravings (Box VM 24)
    - Matlock Batts, undated (mid-19th?), 2 folders with 2 colored engravings (?), on heavy board material (Box VM 24)
    - Monmouthshire, circa 1780, 7 engravings (Box VM 24)
    - Naples, undated, colored engraving (Box VM 24)
    - Norfolk, circa 1780, 1840s, 7 engravings (Box VM 24)
    - Nottinghamshire, circa 1780-1806, 6 engravings (Box VM 24)
    - Old England Pictorial Museum of National Antiquities-- various residential and church interiors, circa 1844, 17 color plates (Box VM 24)
    - Scotland, circa 1780, 1817, and undated, 23 engravings (Box VM 24)
    - Shropshire, circa 1780, 6 engravings (Box VM 24)
    - Somersetshire and Sussex, circa 1780, 7 engravings (Box VM 24)
    - Wales, circa 1776-1780, 1818-1824, and undated, 7 engravings (Box VM 24)
    - Wiltshire & Westmoreland, circa 1780-1788, 11 engravings (Box VM 24)
    - Yorkshire, circa 1780 and undated, 7 engravings (Box VM 24)
    - Various places, Great Britain (including many water scenes--Blackpool, Cumberland, Hartley Hill, Jersey, Newcastle, Portsmouth, and lakes and waterfalls), circa 1770s, 1794-1795, 1845, and undated, 3 folders, 32 engravings and colored engravings (Box VM 24)
    - Various places, Europe, photographs, undated, 2 folders, 4 pages with 8 photograph mounted on double sided board (Box VM 24)
    - Venice, undated, colored engraving (Box VM 24)
    - Alex Ansted prints of France, possibly Italy and Spain, undated, 11 items (Box VM 24)
    - Unsorted or unidentified views, 19th c. and undated, 55 black and white and colored engravings (Box VM 24)
      Chiefly black and white engravings with scenes from Great Britain, but also some of France. Most are rural or coastal landscapes. Artists include Whistler, Dalgliesh, Burgess, Heselline, Huson, Law, Pennell, Edwards.
    - Unsorted views of places, 1700s-1800s, approx. 50 items (Box VM 25-A)
      Chiefly engravings of ruins, castles, estates, churches, and landmarks across England, such as stone crosses and watering places. Also included is a painting of a scene.
  - Subjects Subseries, 1625-1902 and undated, 2 boxes
    Images on a variety of topics and in a variety of formats, including engravings, wood-block prints, photographs, and plates removed from 20th century books and calendars. Especially prominent topics include literary, Biblical, and mythical scenes; pastoral and animal scenes; and painted and photographic copies and reproductions of well-known 18th and 19th century artists. The William Hogarth satire, Credulity, Superstition, and Fanaticism. A Medley, is a famous illustration and critique in the early history of British Methodism. At least one of the Falstaff series by 19th century illustrator George Cruikshank appears to have a signed dedication by the artist. The 1814 Ann Hewson needlepoint/crosstitch sampler, "'Gold' and 'Virtue'," if accurately attributed, would constitute a very early document in the history of Primitive Methodism, generally agreed to have been initiated around 1809 by Hugh Bourne, William Clowes, and others.
    Arranged in alphabetical order by artist, title, or category, with many unsorted small prints housed at the end of the subseries. Oversize prints (larger than 16"x20") are arranged in separate boxes and sequences at the end.
    - Animals: series of portraits of cart and purebred horses; 2 scenes from stag hunting in Scotland by E. Landseer; portrait of tiger by George Cooper; horse and cow entitled "Companions" by J. Foxcroft Cole, 1800 and undated, 15 items (Box VM 25)
    - Birds, undated, 3 items (Box VM 25)
      Color images of birds; "Wagler's Cassicus" and "Ruby Bird of Paradise" from Cassett's Book of Birds, and Paon mâle et femelle from "Oiseaux d'Europe."
    - Caricatures and cartoons (color prints), 1817, 1829, and undated, 7 color prints (Box VM 25)
      Variety of colored prints. Topics include, among others: A Peep into the Green Bag or the Secret Committee of Magnifiers (1817), Le Vrai Amateur (1829), Wrestling with the Sinner (undated), etc.
    - Caricatures and cartoons (b/w prints), 1827-1834 and undated, 5 b/w prints (Box VM 25)
      Variety of b/w engravings and other prints. Includes a series of caricatures by Thomas Landseer in the shape of monkeys, with quotations from Shakespeare, Swift, and Dryden; and an undated, 19th c. series entitled "Bird's-Eye Views of Society." Other titles include: 30 Extraordinary Characters &c. Described in the Work (undated) and The Suicide Club (1834), and A Moment of Agony among others.
    - Chinese depiction of Jesus Christ (color poster), 20th century (Box VM 7)
    - Commentaria in Duodecim Prohetas Minores, 1625 (Box VM 25)
      Frontispiece to a book by R.P. Cornelio Cornelii, published in Antwerp.
    - The Connoisseur Portfolio: Fair Women of the XVIIIth Century, 1902 (Box VM 25)
      Images of real and fictional women by Reynolds, Hoppner, and Opie and engraved by Bartolozzi, Ward, and J.R. Smith.
    - Cruikshank, George, Falstaff: Merry Wives of Windsor images from Sir John Falstaff, 1851, 7 etchings (Box VM 25)
      Drawn and etched by George Cruikshank, Published by Longman & Co. Illustrations of the adventures of Falstaff including, among others: "Sir John Falstaff discovering that Mrs. Ford and Mrs. Page have been making a fool of him," and "Sir John Falstaff thrown into the 'muddy ditch close by the Thames side'" from Acts. I, III, and V of The Merry Wives of Windsor in addition to the volume's frontispiece.
    - Cruikshank, George, Falstaff: Henry IV and V images from "Sir John Falstaff," 1851, 10 etchings (Box VM 25)
      Drawn and etched by George Cruikshank, Published by Longman & Co. Illustrations of the adventures of Falstaff including, among others: "The last scene, in the life of Sir John Falstaff," and "Falstaff giving his account of the affair at Gadshill."
    - Descriptions and Counterfeits of the World's most Distinguished Cities: 1574-1618, Frontispiece facsimile, undated (Box VM 25)
      Color frontispiece print after original.
    - Durand, Armand, Annunciation, undated, circa late 19th century (Box VM 25)
      Lithograph image of the Annunciation, likely after a Dutch Old Master painting.
    - Falstaff: image from King Henry IVth, 1788 (Box VM 25)
      Subject: the last scene of Henry IV printed in anticipation of the publication by S. W. Fores illustrating the play.
    - The Graphic, 1884, 1885, 10 printed pages (Box VM 25)
      Images and text from December 27, 1884 and Summer 1885 editions of The Graphic. Includes stories such as The Ballad of Dame Durden and The Strange Adventures of a Dog-Cart, illustrated in color.
    - Hogarth, William, Credulity, Superstition, and Fanaticism. A Medley, 1762 Mar. 15 (Box VM 25)
      Designed and engraved by William Hogarth. Satire of Methodism and Methodist preachers, including John Wesley and George Whitefield. Original release is only date on item, but heavy paper is more similar to early 19th century re-strikes.
    - Linguarum Vett. Septentrionalium Thesaurus Grammatico-Criticus et Archaeologicus, 1705 (Box VM 25)
      Volume with autograph dedication by the author (George Hickes) to a Mr. James St. Amand.
    - Methodist Book Room: "Interior of the Wesleyan-Methodist Book-Room, City-Road, London," circa 1840 (Box VM 25)
    - Miscellaneous Prints, undated (Box VM 25)
      Includes: page of printed autograph samples of the Clifford Family; religious scenes; mythological scenes (including engraving of Brittania with lion).
    - Our National Church: the Ægis of Liberty, Fraternity, Equality, published by John Heywood, 1883 June (Box VM 27)
      Cartoon satirizing "the National Church and its Parties" in relation to various sects and heresies, including Low and High Church, Agnosticism, Darwinism, and many other groups and topics.
    - Pastoral landscapes and scenes, undated, 29 plates (Box VM 25)
      Includes: color images printed by Leighton Bros., color plates of country images, seasonal scenes, birds and insects from various unidentified sources.
    - Printed reproductions of pastel and oil works, undated (early 20th c.?), 13 items (Box VM 25)
      Includes: color reproductions of British and Continental artworks after artists such as Josef Israels, George Frederic Watts, James Ward, and Frans Mieris.
    - Rogers, J. after H. Singleton, The Departure of Cain, undated (Box VM 25)
    - "Select Pieces" Written by Mas H. Barker at Sutcliffe & Son's Academy, Wright Street, Manchester, 1869 (Box VM 25)
      Subject: view of a fortified city with individuals in the foreground. Short prescriptive texts inside include "Advocacy," "Procrastination Continued," etc. and short proverb entries for "April" and "May."
    - Scene (unidentified)--etching depicting a beggar and other individuals in a rocky landscape, undated (Box VM 25)
    - Unidentified people and characters (b/w prints), 1793 and undated, 5 b/w prints (Box VM 25)
      Subjects include, among others: an allegory of charity, Triton, Joseph.
    - Unidentified people and characters (color prints), 1813 and undated, 14 color images (Box VM 25)
      Subjects include, among others: a gypsy woman, children playing marbles, allegorical depictions of "Faith" and "Hope."
    - Unsorted small prints, 1700s-1900s, 5 envelopes, circa 180 items (Box VM 25-A)
      Includes group of small prints by R. Seymour, with scenes from Christmas events, a christening dinner, street scenes, and other social scenes and portraits of individual types. Also a colored engraving portraying an African dance, "Singular Custom of the Ashantees during the Annual Yam Feast," 1828.
    - Hewson, Ann, "Gold" and "Virtue," needlepoint/crossstitch sampler, 1814, 1 item, framed (Box VM 26)
      Text, two quatrains on "Gold" and "Virtue," set amid illustrations of trees, birds, flowers in vases, etc. Embroidered inscription: "I have done this that you may see,/what care my parents took of me. Ann Hewson, Her Sampler done in the 10th year of her Age 1814." Notes on back about Hewsons: "probably Primitive Methodists, of Holton-on[?]-Clay."
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box VM 27)
    - Miscellaneous maps, 1887 and undated (Box VM 27)
    - Drawings and paintings, undated (Box VM 27)
    - Landscapes, 1733, 1739, and undated (Box VM 27)
      Includes The East View of Winchester Palace, 1730; The North East View of Lolworth Castle, 1733; and The View Near Alnwick, undated.